Okay בוקר טוב. boker tov. Today's דף daf is ק"ו Kuf Vav
and we're in the middle of a lot of discussion about קידוש
Kiddush and הבדלה Havdalah and we just finished with a story about
a person who comes home מוצאי שבת, Motzaei Shabbat, he only has
one כוס kos of wine, so what's he going to do? He
can't and either he was eating or תוספות Tosafot says he's planning
on eating and needs to use that כוס, kos, that cup of
wine for ברכת המזון Birkat Hamazon but he also needs to use
it for הבדלה. Havdalah. So he goes ahead and eats his meal,
by the way תוספות Tosafot says we even allow him to have
his meal first then to eat before הבדלה Havdalah because we want
to enable him to have that כוס, kos, that glass of wine
when he finishes ברכת המזון. Birkat Hamazon. So he goes ahead and
does that and then at the end he uses that cup for
both ברכת המזון, Birkat Hamazon, the ברכה bracha and for הבדלה. Havdalah.
Now the גמרא Gemara says that there's a lot of things that
can be learned from this,
eight things, right. So some of the key ones we mentioned yesterday
was number one that ברכת המזון Birkat Hamazon always requires a glass
of wine, because if not, why is this an issue? And as
תוספות Tosafot points out, the simple sense is even when an individual
does ברכת המזון, Birkat Hamazon, you know, not even you don't need
three, you don't need ten. I mean there's other opinions in the
גמרא Gemara that ברכת המזון Birkat Hamazon does not need wine, but
this certainly sounds like it does. We of course know that it's
our practice, you know, I don't know of anybody who's מקפיד makpid
to have it when there's one. I guess there's some people מקפיד
makpid to have it when there's three. Anyway, that's one thing.
If he had only one cup,
yes, if
he was to make two cups from this, would it do the
order?
Well, we're going to discuss that. Okay. So that's, so the גמרא
Gemara says the other thing, so the order's an interesting point. The
גמרא Gemara says the other thing you see is that there's a
minimum amount, because if there wasn't a minimum amount of wine, just
split the one cup into two cups. Now Joe makes a good
point, Joe makes a good point that if some, that, you know,
we do actually say that you can mix your wine with water.
The גמרא Gemara didn't give that as an option, it's interesting it
didn't point that out, but it could be assuming that you already
have mixed it and then you can't mix beyond a certain point,
but that actually is a good point. But the other thing the
גמרא Gemara says you learn from this is that if you drink
a little bit, the wine becomes פגום, pagum, unusable, because if even
because it let, maybe there should just be a, you know, maybe
there's a רביעית revi'it and a little sip, so you make it
on the רביעית revi'it and a little sip, you take the little
sip and you use the remainder of the רביעית revi'it for the
next for הבדלה. Havdalah. So you see that even a little sip
makes it unusable. What? My question yesterday about? Oh,
we'll get to that. Anyway. And you see that you have to
take a sip, that you can't just make ברכת המזון Birkat Hamazon
or הבדלה Havdalah without taking a sip, because again if you could
do that then you wouldn't have the problem of פגום. pagum. So
you learn all of these important points from it. So let's take
a look now, the גמרא Gemara lists some more things. Just let
me, let's get a little started and then we'll go back and
discuss them. Very top of ק"ו עמוד א', Kuf Vav Amud Aleph,
ושמע
מינה, u'shma mina, or I guess the last three words on ק"ו
עמוד ב': Kuf Vav Amud Bet: ושמע מינה טעם מבדיל. u'shma mina
ta'am mavdia. You see that once even if you're normally not, we
know you're not allowed to eat before הבדלה Havdalah and קידוש, Kiddush,
here we allowed you to, but or maybe in the scenario even
if we didn't allow you to, בדיעבד b'diavad a person ate before
הבדלה Havdalah or ate before קידוש, Kiddush, does that invalidate them from
making הבדלה Havdalah and from making קידוש? Kiddush? So we'll see, but
the at least here you see it does not, he's allowed to
make הבדלה. Havdalah. ושמע מינה u'shma mina top of ק"ו עמוד א':
Kuf Vav Amud Aleph: אומרים שתי קדושות על כוס אחד. omrin shtei
kedushot al kos echad. You also see that you can say two
קדושות kedushot for one כוס, kos, meaning because here, meaning not really
two קדושות, kedushot, but you can say both ברכת המזון Birkat Hamazon
and הבדלה Havdalah on the same כוס, kos, even though we had
an issue before about מצוות חבילות חבילות, mitzvot chavilot chavilot, bundling up
מצוות, mitzvot, using the same cup which really gives identity to the
ritual act and using it for two distinct ritual acts, particularly here
where it's not like הבדלה Havdalah and קידוש Kiddush which are related,
but it's about ברכת המזון Birkat Hamazon and קידוש. Kiddush. Nevertheless, as
the גמרא Gemara said earlier, certainly if you have no other choice,
you only have one כוס, kos, that is acceptable. Okay, so that's
another thing you see. ושמע מינה, u'shma mina, and we see from
this בית שמאי היא ואליבא דרבי יהודה, Beit Shammai hi v'aliba d'Rabbi
Yehuda, that the author of this ברייתא Baraita is בית שמאי Beit
Shammai according to רבי יהודה. Rabbi Yehuda. What does that mean? Because
the ברייתא Baraita said the order of the הבדלה, Havdalah, the ברייתא
Baraita said, was יין, yayin, מאור, maor, בשמים, besamim, and הבדלה, Havdalah,
which is the opposite of what we do, right? We do יין
בשמים—not yayin besamim the opposite, but the middle two were reversed. We
do יין בשמים נר yayin besamim ner and הבדלה, Havdalah, and the
גמרא Gemara before said that that, at least according to רבי יהודה,
Rabbi Yehuda, that issue of order is a debate of בית הלל
ובית שמאי. Beit Hillel v'Beit Shammai. So the order by this ברייתא,
Baraita, first doing אש aish before בשמים, besamim, according to רבי יהודה,
Rabbi Yehuda, is a בית שמאי Beit Shammai position, not a בית
הלל Beit Hillel position. Okay, so that's more like tying up a
loose end from before. Now now we're going to focus on this
issue about פגום, pagum, the wine. Okay. So we said before that
one of the things you learned was that if you took a
little sip you made it invalid, because wine after just a little
sip—and use the rest for, for, you know, for הבדלה. Havdalah. רב
אשי אמר טעמו פגמו וכוס של ברכה צריך שיעור, Rav Ashi amar
ta'amo pagmo v'kos shel bracha tzarich shiur, the two things you thought
you could learn from that ברייתא, Baraita, one is that a little
taste makes the rest unusable, and number two that there's a minimum
amount, because if there wasn't a minimum amount, just divide it into
two cups, חדא מילתא היא, chada milta hi, that— That's really in
that ברייתא, braita, you can't prove that those are separate issues. Maybe
it's all one concern, maybe it's just the concern of the minimum
amount. והכי קאמר, vehachi kamar, and here's what it says. מאי טעמא
טעמו פגמו? mai ta'ama ta'amo pagmo? Why when you take the sip,
can you not use the rest of the wine for הבדלה, havdala,
if you were to take a sip for benching? משום דכוס של
ברכה צריך שיעור, mishum dechos shel bracha tzarich shiur, because maybe there's
only a precise amount. Meaning what he says is, who told you
there was a רביעית revi'is plus a sip? Maybe there's only an
exactly a רביעית. revi'is. If the scenario is there's exactly a רביעית,
revi'is, all you can prove is that you need a minimum amount.
You can't prove that the sip, you know, does some special thing
on its own. Maybe all the sip did was it lowered it
to less than a רביעית. revi'is. So the way תוספות Tosafot says
is he doesn't really disagree with the הלכה, halacha, though the רשב"ם
Rashbam thinks he does, but at least he's saying you can't prove
that other point from the ברייתא. braita. The ברייתא braita isn't clear
that you have any more than exactly a רביעית, revi'is, and if
all you have is exactly a רביעית, revi'is, the only thing you
can prove is that there's a need for a minimum amount, and
once you take the sip, you no longer have the minimum amount.
So now we're going to look at whether it can or can't
be proved from the ברייתא. braita. The גמרא Gemara certainly put out
there an idea that even a small sip invalidates, even if you
have enough leftover, and that's this idea of פוגם. pogem. פוגם pogem
to mean like, you know, sort of like like sullies it, but
actually פגימה pgima more literally is like a like little like a
little like a notch in something, indentation, right. Like when your אתרוג
etrog is פגום, pagum, you know, so it means metaphorically like there's
some type of a, you know, something missing or something that's stigmatized,
but much more it also means something is like physically actually, you
know, been taken away from it. And this is the idea, does
the wine somehow get labeled as used wine that can no longer
be used for another ritual act, even if you have enough of
it left over? Like I mentioned the other day, it's sort of
like we just got, you know, not too long ago we had
הושענא רבה, Hoshana Raba, you know, once you beat the ערבות, aravot,
you can't lend it to somebody else to use again, right, like
it's used. So is that that idea that the wine is considered
it's already been used and can't be used again now for a
for another act? So let's take a look at the at what
the גמרא Gemara says about this idea of פגם. pgam. So it
says like this. Okay, רב
יעקב בר אידי קפיד אכצרא פגימא. Rav Yaakov bar Idi kapid achatzra
pgima. רב יעקב בר אידי Rav Yaakov bar Idi was concerned not
even to use a פגום pagum pitcher. Now again, meaning number one,
it wasn't a כוס. kos. So maybe he just drank a little
bit straight from the pitcher. Now you could say it means even
if you poured off a little from the pitcher for your own
wine, you can't use what's left in the pitcher. That would be
like crazy. What, every time I pour from something, I can't use
what's left? And there's another
גמרא Gemara anyway—no, חביתא chavita is more later, חצרא chatzra is more
like a pitcher—anyway from the next from there's another גמרא Gemara makes
it clear that if you want to avoid פגם, pgam, what you
do is you say בורא פרי הגפן borei pri hagafen and then
you pour into a little cup and you drink from the other
cup and then the original thing does not become פגום. pagum. So
clearly the scenario had to be you drank a little straight from
the pitcher. But the point is פגם pgam is not only it's
not just חבילות חבילות chavilos chavilos as I mean I said it
before maybe a little imprecisely, it's not just because you used it
for a מצוה, mitzvah, it's that you drank from it. It's like
almost like cooties or something, you got your saliva in it, but
not not really, a הלכה'דיק halachadik an idea. But if you drank
from the wine, it can't be used anymore for a ritual act.
So even if you took a little drink even straight from the
pitcher, okay, it cannot be used, even if it wasn't like in
the context of a כוס יין. kos yayin. רב אידי בר שישא
קפיד אכסא פגימא. Rav Idi bar Shisha kapid achasa pgima. He was
concerned about the כוס kos פגום, pagum, maybe not the pitcher, not
clear if he had a different position. מר בר רב אשי קפיד
אפילו אחביתא פגימא. Mar bar Rav Ashi kapid afilu achavita pgima. Even
the barrel, even if you took a little sip from the barrel.
Again, not so
hygienic, people that drink throughout a—well again, so it's hard to imagine
that scenario, and you would have thought it meant that once you
take from the barrel and you can't use the rest, but then
that would be again be like crazy in terms of the implications,
and as I said from other גמרות Gemaras it's clear not that
it's just if you pour off it's okay. But maybe what the
גמרא Gemara means is the גמרא, Gemara, there's other גמרות Gemaras that
do speak about doing like tasting, like you stick a straw in
it and you do a you sip a little to get a
little taste about what's the quality of the wine is, so that
could be a more understandable scenario. Now you could say big deal,
I just did a little taste, you know, I just I wasn't
really even seriously drinking from it. No, once you took a little,
it's the rest is not used, meaning having to do a ritual
act. Yeah, using the rest, no, not in the context of the
ritual. Once you took a drink from something, from wine, directly from
this container, the remainder cannot be used. If you pour off, then
it only relates to the wine in the container you're drinking from,
but if I went ahead and I took a little sip of
the wine in the barrel to see whether it was good or
not, having nothing to do with doing any ritual, I was פוגם
pogem the wine and now it can't be used.
Yes, מר בר רב אשי,
Mar bar
Rav
Ashi, but in the medieval Europe, you'd have a tap at the
bottom of the barrel or a hole that was plugged up, so
you can imagine somebody coming down to the wine cellar, making קידוש
kiddush on the barrel and then, you know, opening it up and
having a little.
Right. Right, but what I'm saying to Michael is that even if
the initial use wasn't used for... But what I'm saying to Michael
is that is that is that even if the initial use wasn't
used for a ritual, even if the first
use you make קידוש Kiddush on the whole barrel and then sip.
I understand.
I understand. I understand. But what I want to make clear is
the idea of פגום pagum is the first time you sip from
it could have been for any purpose and that makes that makes
what's left invalid. It's not necessarily this idea that there's like a
מצות חבילות חבילות, mitzvot chavilot chavilot, it was used for a מצוה.
mitzvah. And again maybe my example about the ערבות aravot was distracting
and I shouldn't have given it. But the point is once you
use once you drink from it from directly from the barrel or
the cup or whatever, anything left in the container you drank from,
think of it more as cooties and saliva, which again is not
really what the הלכה halacha is based on, but conceptually anything left
in that container cannot be used. It's like it's somehow been
been already already sullied. Yes.
Can this wine if he cannot drink, can this wine be drunk
by somebody else?
You can drink it, you just can't use it for you just
can't use it for קידוש. Kiddush.
Okay, but can another man use?
No. You mean somebody else use it for קידוש? Kiddush? No. It
can't be used objectively for קידוש Kiddush or for הבדלה havdalah by
anybody else.
Right. Right. Exactly. Exactly. Yes. Now now what's the end of the
story with this? So first of all the רשב״ם Rashbam points out
the language of קפיד. kapid. קפיד kapid sounds like it was his
own preference, it was his own concern. He was being careful about
it. So if you look at תוספות, Tosafot, תוספות Tosafot says קפידא
כדסברא ליה. kapida k'desavra lei.
So it says פירש רשב״ם peireish Rashbam and I mean I could
read in the רשב״ם Rashbam too but I want to also see
the end of תוספות. Tosafot. דקפיד לכתחילה דוקא ואם אין לו אלא
פגום יקדש עליו. dekapid lechatchila davka veim ein lo ela pagum yekadesh
alav.
That's only a לכתחילה. lechatchila. בדיעבד bedieved you could use פגום. pagum.
He says ותימא אם כן היכי תירצו לאכול קודם הבדלה משום כפידא
דפגימה, veteima im kein heichi tirzu leechol kodem havdalah mishum kfida depagima,
then how come according to how תוספות Tosafot understood they allowed you
to have your whole meal before הבדלה? havdalah? So it's only a
לכתחילה. lechatchila. What's the big deal? So he says I don't really
think the רשב״ם Rashbam is right. I really think it's a בדיעבד
bedieved concern. מיהו ראוי רשב״ם לסמוך עליו בשעת הדחק. mihu ra'uy Rashbam
lismoch alav b'sha'at hadechak. So I thought that was just so fascinating.
It's not like an opinion in the גמרא Gemara is ראוי לסמוך
עליו. ra'uy lismoch alav. Here he's talking about essentially a contemporary, right?
And but it's again seeing that I don't really agree with him
but what if you really don't have any other wine? בדיעבד סומך
הדחק. bedieved someich hadechak.
Now the other thing that's not in our גמרא Gemara at all
but is in the ירושלמי Yerushalmi and the רא״ש Rosh quotes it
and this is critically important is is there a way to fix
the פגימה? pagima? And I'll just read you quickly one line from
the רא״ש Rosh and the רא״ש Rosh says the following. He says
I'll tell you in a minute.
It's סימן י״א siman yud-aleph in the רא״ש Rosh and the רא״ש
Rosh says like this. What the רא״ש Rosh says I'll just read
it to you just one line. He says ובירושלמי משמע. uv'Yerushalmi mashma.
What page? In my edition it's קל״ב kuf-lamed-bet on the first column.
He says ובירושלמי משמע uv'Yerushalmi mashma near the bottom of the first
column. ובירושלמי משמע דכוס פגום מרבה עליו כל שהוא ומכשירו. uv'Yerushalmi mashma
dekos pagum marbeh alav kol shehu umachshiro. ובירושלמי משמע דכוס פגום מרבה
עליו כל שהוא ומכשירו ואפילו במים יכול לתקנו. uv'Yerushalmi mashma dekos pagum
marbeh alav kol shehu umachshiro va'afilu b'mayim yachol letakno. So here goes
your question Joe which is a different version of it. You take
a little sip now if you add to it you've now it
no longer has that status of being drunk from. Now it's like
a fresh cup. Okay or conceptually you've restored what is lacking but
you don't actually have to fill up the equal amount of what
you took away. You just have to somehow give it a new
identity. It's now not one that's been drunk from. It's now new
wine, fresh wine, because a little bit has been added to it.
So then of course the question is so why didn't he do
that in this case? Why didn't he just take one cup make
ברכת המזון, birkat hamazon, take a little sip, add to it, and
then do הבדלה? havdalah? So that's the obvious question and he asks
about that. ותימא אם כן הכא למה לא יבדיל על כוס יתקנו
במים ויכשירנו בברכת המזון. veteima im kein hacha lama lo yavdil al
kos yetakno b'mayim veyachshirenu bivrakat hamazon. ויש לומר veyesh lomar and
this is like I told you Joe דכבר היה מזוג כדינו dechvar
haya mazug kedino that it already was fully mixed with water and
any extra water would not be acceptable and there's no other wine.
This is all the wine you've got. So it has to be
a very but it doesn't sound that way. From our גמרא Gemara
it sounds like there's no way to fix this. But the הלכה
halacha is actually ruled in accordance with the ירושלמי Yerushalmi and actually
so this is why everybody does this right? You make whatever הבדלה
havdalah you take a little sip you don't want to drink the
whole rest of the thing so you add in a little wine
into the כוס kos and then you pour it back into your
into your bottle and that's okay. Now of course doesn't right so
it's not a real cooties thing but now you've made it not
a used but you've made it fresh. Now actually it's not the
idea is and it does again focus like we see on the
גמרא Gemara on the on the container you drank from. That's the
one that the focus is on because if instead of pouring from
the bottle into the כוס kos I just said what's the difference?
It's all going to get mixed up anyway. I'll just pour from
the כוס kos back into the bottle right? So that doesn't fix
it. That actually because then you're taking bad wine and you're mixing
it with you're not making the bad wine good. You're not changing
the status of the כוס. kos. You're taking the bad wine and
putting it now into the bottle. Now if the הלכה halacha is
is that if the bottle then it depends what has רוב. rov.
If the bottle has רוב rov בדיעבד bedieved it's okay. If the
wine had if the כוס kos had רוב rov בדיעבד bedieved it's
not good. But but לכתחילה lechatchila you're not supposed to do that.
So that's exactly the practice that first you pour a drop in
and then you pour it back and you don't worry about your
cooties. Okay and
I should... It's not alcohol percentage. It's percentage of original of original
grape juice content plus added water. That's the issue of further diluting
it. It's not a question of percentage of alcohol. It's a question
of percentage of grape juice content, as it were, original wine versus
additional wine and water and additional water. Yes.
In a מחלוקת *machloket* between בבלי *Bavli* and ירושלמי *Yerushalmi*, we don't
usually hold by...
Well, it's not a מחלוקת *machloket*. It's, you know, it's to be
understood that the ירושלמי's *Yerushalmi's* adding a point that's not in the
בבלי *Bavli*, and even though implicitly the בבלי *Bavli* could be said
doesn't agree because otherwise it would have said it, if there's a
way to say they're not really disagreeing, I mean, but that's a
question. But, you know, and again as you could already see from
תוספות's Tosafos, *Tosafot's* שעת הדחק *sha'at hadechak*, you know, there was a
need to find a way to solve this problem. And that gave
pressure also to, you know, to incorporate the ירושלמי *Yerushalmi*. Yes.
Dov, do you know, are grape juices these days already considered diluted?
No, our grape juice is like, you know, it says, like I
mean most of it says 100% grape juice and so. Now of
course the question is, and Dov, we spoke about this before, like
I never understood this idea, like what, the wine before there had
what, a higher, you know like what, like a higher viscosity? Is
that really true? And so Dov, you had a theory about that,
didn't you?
I saw somewhere that no, that wine was wine, but some cultures
you added more water to it. That's how you drank wine.
Oh, oh just because you didn't have soda and you didn't have
and you didn't have lemonade and you didn't have this and you
wanted a sweeter drink but you didn't want to be getting drunk,
you had more of a diluted form of it.
That could very well be what some people, let's see,
the viscosity from the way that you drank wine was watered down.
Right. I mean that was just, right. Right. Right. Right.
So, I saw in other places you just drank it straight up.
Uh-huh. Right. Okay, yes. What? Ice cubes. Ice cubes? What do you
mean? Ice cubes. Oh, ice cubes.
Some people put ice cubes in wine.
Right, right. But the הלכה Halakha *halacha* you can dilute your wine
a three-to-one water-to-wine ratio and it's still and it's still considered הלכתית
*halachically* wine. And the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* makes it sound like they
always would dilute it, you know, so that's again it's hard for
us to imagine drinking wine that diluted and still treating it as
wine.
The though the רשב״ם *Rashbam* says its חביות *chaviyot* are קטנות *ktanot*,
so it's not the big barrel according to...
Right. He wants to, he's trying to understand how do you jump
from a barrel. Right. Okay. All right. Dov, you want to say
something?
ותהא
רעב לשתות *V'tehei ra'ev lishtot*.
Oh, so we'll discuss that later about using, about using liquor. Let's,
let's keep on going
on the issue of grape juice. What? The grape juice is often
reconstituted.
Right, so that's a question. So there was a reconstituted grape juice.
So, so I still remember that there's a תשובה *teshuva*, I think
it's in the ציץ אליעזר *Tzitz Eliezer* that somebody says, "Can you,
you know, can you make קידוש Kiddush *Kiddush* over reconstituted grape juice?"
What's that? What is reconstituted?
They basically, it's like, it's like powdered milk. Like, you know, you
take out all of the water content, you ship... Well, I don't
know what they do, they ship it, no, they all do it
at the factory, but it's a way you ship then the, you
know, solid matter and then they add water when they get it
there and so it makes shipping costs a lot less. So somebody,
I think it was the ציץ אליעזר *Tzitz Eliezer*, "Can you make,
you know, use reconstituted grape juice for קידוש Kiddush. *Kiddush*?" And he
says, "Why don't you ask me whether first of all whether you
can make a בורא פרי הגפן Borei pri hagafen. *Borei Peri HaGafen*
or not? You know, why don't you ask me whether you can
use grape juice for קידוש Kiddush *Kiddush*, let alone reconstituted grape juice?"
So there's definitely issues with that. All right. So let's go on.
So now the ברייתא braita *braita* says like this.
One minute. Okay fine. תנו רבנן *Tanu rabanan*. Now we get to
a general issues around the basic idea of this הלכה halacha, *halacha*
of קידוש Kiddush. על היין al hayayin *Kiddush al hayayin*. זכור את
יום השבת Zachor et yom haShabbat. לקדשו *Zachor et yom haShabbat l'kadsho*.
זכרהו על היין Zachrehu al hayayin. *Zochrehu al hayayin*. So here's the
biblical basis. Remember שבת Shabbat *Shabbat*. What does remember mean? It means
to remember it or like maybe like זכרהו *zochrehu* also means like
to, like mention it, right? Articulate it, commemorate it over wine. אין
לי אלא ביום *Ein li ela b'yom*. I only know you're supposed
to do it in the daytime. יום השבת *Yom haShabbat*. בלילה מניין
*Balaila minayin*? How do I know you do it at night? תלמוד
לומר Talmud lomar *Talmud lomar* זכור Zachor את יום השבת לקדשו *Zachor
et yom haShabbat l'kadsho*. Which is, huh? Like, what did that say?
You didn't say, anyway that's יום *yom*. So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*
says that. בלילה מניין *Balaila minayin*? What do you mean how do
you know you do it at night? אדרבה *Adaraba*, the opposite. עיקר
קידושא בליליא הוא *Ikar kiddusha b'leilya hu*. קדשיה *Kadsheihu*. The basic idea
of קידוש Kiddush. *Kiddush* is at night. Why? Because all at, you
demarcate it and you pronounce it at the beginning. That's when it
becomes sanctified. That's when you declare it. ותיקדש *V'tikadesh*. When it becomes
sanctified. תחלת יומא בעי קידושא *Techilat yoma bei kiddusha*. You have to
sanctify the beginning of the day. ותו *V'tu*, בלילה מניין *balaila minayin*?
תלמוד לומר *Talmud lomar*, זכור יום *Zachor yom*. What do you mean
how do you know at night? Because it says remember the day.
So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says, so תנא מהדר אליליא *tanna mehadar
a'leilya*, you're looking to show that you do it at night? וכנסב
ליה קרא דיממא *V'kanasiv lei kra d'yimama*? And you caught a פסוק
pasuk *pasuk* that speaks about doing it the day? הכי קאמר *Hachi
ka'amar*. Okay you're right. You know what? The text is a little
corrupt. Here's how you have to read it. זכור את יום השבת
לקדשו *Zachor et yom haShabbat l'kadsho*. זכרהו על היין Zachrehu al hayayin
*Zochrehu al hayayin*. Declare it, commemorate it over wine בכניסתו *b'chnisato*. Now
clearly, presumably, where is it sort of given its, you know, identity,
its declaration? At the beginning. So that would tell me אין לי
אלא בלילה *ein li ela balaila*. So it's reversed. is the order.
So from the idea that it's not the word יום but conceptually
it's about sort of declaring its identity, sanctifying it, that's when it
begins at night. ביום מניין? Bayom minayin? How do I know there's
an idea of קידוש Kiddush. during the day? תלמוד לומר זכור את
יום השבת. There's also an idea during the day.
Because it already says זכור את
השבת.
Zachor
et haShabbat.
I guess. Okay. Now ביום מאי מברך? Bayom mai mivarech? What ברכה
bracha do you make at the day? Right? We've always been talking
about making the whole thing at night, right? At the day we
know we only make a בורא פרי הגפן. Borei pri hagafen. The
פסוקים psukim before aren't really halachically part of the קידוש. Kiddush? So
the גמרא Gemara doesn't, you know, is trying to figure it out
this day so it's now introducing this idea of קידוש Kiddush, at
the day. So ביום מאי מברך? Bayom mai mivarech? So אמר רב
יהודה Amar Rav Yehuda בורא פרי הגפן. Borei pri hagafen? Okay, that's
it? Just בורא פרי הגפן? Borei pri hagafen So רב אשי Rav
Ashi איקלע למחוזא. Iklai l'Mechuza. רב אשי Rav Ashi came to מחוזא.
Mechuza. אמרו ליה, Amru lei, they said to him לקדש לן מר
קידושא רבא Likadesh lan mar Kiddusha Rabba which was שבת Shabbat day.
They said, let Master make for us the big קידוש. Kiddush Why
is it called... so the רשב"ם Rashbam says this קידושא רבא, Kiddusha
Rabba, it could be a little bit like a euphemism. The רשב"ם
Rashbam says that קידושא רבא Kiddusha Rabba because the בורא פרי הגפן
Borei pri hagafen. is said at every קידוש. Kiddush, So that component
is sort of is universal, but it's funny that it's called קידושא
רבא. Kiddusha Rabba. It might be a little euphemism. Okay, anyways, the
Master should say for us the big קידוש. Kiddush So הבו ליה,
Havu lei, they gave him a cup of wine. So סבר, Savar,
he said מאי ניהו קידושא רבא? Mai nihu Kiddusha Rabba? What is
this big קידוש? Kiddush, Like here you are, you're put on the
spot, everybody's looking around, waiting for you to make קידוש, Kiddush, you
don't know what the heck you're supposed to do. I never heard
of this big קידוש Kiddush on שבת Shabbat day. So and it's
going to seem like not only didn't he know about this phrase
big קידוש, Kiddush it's going to sound like he never heard of
the concept of קידוש Kiddush on שבת Shabbat day. Okay, so he
doesn't know what the heck they were talking about. So אמרי, Amri,
so he said, so he said, so like you know here he's
thinking on the spot how to handle this. He says מכדי, Michdee,
let's take a look. Let's think about this. כל הברכות כולן בורא
פרי הגפן אמרי ברישא. Kol habrachot kulan Borei pri hagafen amri b'reisha.
First of all, they gave him a cup of wine. Second of
all, he says any type of thing you do, you know, like
this ritual thing like קידוש, Kiddush, ברכת המזון, Birkat Hamazon, whatever, you
always start הבדלה, Havdalah, the first ברכה bracha you make is בורא
פרי הגפן. Borei pri hagafen. Okay, so... that's פסוקים, psukim,
that's not the... that's not the actual thing itself. That's something that
was added later. So every single thing like the הנני מוכן Hineni
muchan or ויכולו, Vayechulu, that's not really halachically part of a part
of the ברכה. bracha. The ברכה bracha starts with בורא פרי הגפן.
Borei pri hagafen.
So he says they gave me a cup of wine, I know
I have to say בורא פרי הגפן. Borei pri hagafen. I know
I'm going to say it first because whenever you have wine you
say it first. So I'll start at least I'll start off with
the right foot, I'll start by saying בורא פרי הגפן. Borei pri
hagafen. Okay? So אמר בורא פרי הגפן. Amar Borei pri hagafen. So
he said בורא פרי הגפן. Borei pri hagafen. ואגבייה, V'agbeiyeh, and he
worked schlepping it out. Okay? Maybe he was waiting for somebody to
nudge him and say נו נו נו, nu nu nu, you know,
מקדש היום Mekadesh hayom or something, who knows what he was hoping
for? But he was schlepping out בורא פרי הגפן. Borei pri hagafen.
חזייה לההוא סבא, Chazeiyeh l'hahu saba, he saw a certain older person,
דגחין ושתי, d'gachin v'shatei, who was bending down and starting to drink.
So he figured, oh, okay, so we're done!
That's it. So קרי אנפשיה Karei anafsheih החכם עיניו בראשו. Hechacham einav
b'rosho. Oh, look, I had some good foresight. So it works out
that all they're talking about is בורא פרי הגפן. Borei pri hagafen,
נו, Nu, that I can handle. Now what's fascinating about this is
it makes it sound like not only he didn't know the phrase
קידושא רבא, Kiddusha Rabba, he didn't know about this whole practice of
making קידוש, Kiddush of calling this קידוש Kiddush, on שבת Shabbos day.
And it's רב אשי! Rav Ashi! Instead of honestly asking something, you
know, I'm not sure. He starts taking it and looking around and
seeing getting some cues from the crowd.
Exactly. And it's רב אשי!
Rav Ashi! What a shame! Hiding behind the רש"י Rashi in the
book so the teacher won't call on him.
There you go. Now right, and it is רב אשי Rav Ashi
and it's quite late and I should say that... now because the
ברייתא braita the גמרא Gemara quoted, it sounds like it was already
Tannaitic this idea. But... wait a minute... but the point is like
this: mostly there's, you know, it's understood that קידוש Kiddush is דאורייתא.
de'oraita.
Some even say הבדלה Havdalah is דאורייתא. de'oraita. זכור as I mentioned
this the other day means remember it at the beginning and at
the end and demarcated both ways. קידוש Kiddush during the day is
pretty... is pretty, you know, pretty much unanimously or whatever the consensus
is not דאורייתא de'oraita and is considered to be something else. And
not only is that, but if it's only בורא פרי הגפן, Borei
pri hagafen, of course the question is to what extent do you
even consider it like a קידוש, Kiddush right? And for example, just
to underscore that point, you remember the גמרא Gemara. earlier mentioned about...
about... about waiting, you know, for your wine if you only had
so much wine or whatever make sure you had wine during your
meal because that's important for כבוד שבת. kevod Shabbat. So and the
רמב"ם Rambam actually says, and I mentioned this before, that there's an
idea of having all three meals, including שלוש סעודות shalosh seudot על
היין for a sense of עונג שבת. oneg Shabbat. So to what
degree is... I mean we allow ourselves to think it's קידוש Kiddush.
because we say all those פסוקים. psukim. But if you're really just
saying בורא פרי הגפן, Borei Pri HaGafen, to what degree is it
different than just saying that you should have your meal with wine
as a part of עונג שבת? oneg Shabbat? And the basic difference
is, I mean the ברייתא Braisa calls it קידוש, Kiddush. but okay,
but the basic difference is is that you're not supposed to eat
your meal until you make קידוש Kiddush. first. Okay? And that's what
sort of gives the... for the... if you want to ask for
the רמב"ם, Rambam, how is קידוש Kiddush. in the second meal different
than wine in the third meal? And the only difference is that
this has to start the meal, right, and has to come out
precede the meal, whereas the other idea is the wine comes during
the meal. But you understand this question
just to... during שבת Shabbos, day. Okay, yes, Michelle, did you have
a question?
I was going to ask is the ברייתא is bringing פסוקים psukim
which would imply that they think that it might be דאורייתא? De'oraysa?
Yeah, but you never know, you know, whether it's an אסמכתא asmachta
or not. Now I want to say something about this issue about
יין yayin and הבדלה. Havdalah. If you take a look at תוספות,
Tosafos זכרהו על היין. Zachrehu al hayayin, Right, תוספות Tosafos says the
following: דזכירה כתיבא על היין. Dezchira kesiva al hayayin. זכרו
כיין הלבנון, Zichro k'yayin halevanon, right, his memory is like the wine
of the Lebanon.
נזכירה דודיך מיין. Nazkira dodecha miyayin. Now of course none of that
means that you say a זכירה zechira over wine. It means that
wine is something that is connected strongly to evoking memories, but okay,
but you could sort of see how that then leads to, so
therefore things that you're supposed to make significant you connect to
wine. והאי זכירה היינו קידוש דמקדשים בפה דויכולו לא
מצינו על כוס אלא בתפילה. V'hai zechira hainu kiddush d'mikadshim b'peh d'vayechulu
lo matzinu al kos ela bitfila. ויכולו Vayechulu in the גמרא Gemara
never occurs when you make קידוש Kiddush. at home. It's only a
practice to say ויכולו Vayechulu according to the גמרא Gemara, at least,
or whatever. It's even ויכולו Vayechulu isn't even in the גמרא. Gemara?
But anyway, תוספות Tosafos says the practice only originated in שול. shul.
Now why did it originate in שול? shul? And why to say
it in שול? shul? He says in the דאוונינג, davening, שאמרו שבת
דלא נתקן. She'amru Shabbos d'lo niskan. Actually right, I meant I misstated
this. Meaning, yes, it is, ויכולו Vayechulu is in תפילה tefilla in
שבת, Shabbos, but never on the כוס. kos. And why was it
in, why according to the גמרא Gemara do you have ויכולו Vayechulu
in תפילה? tefilla? ולא נתקן על הכוס אלא להוציא בניו ובני ביתו.
V'lo niskan al hakos ela l'hotzi banav uvnei beiso. Only because at
home people haven't דאוונד davened מעריב, Maariv, right? So ויכולו Vayechulu of
מעריב Maariv is in the גמרא, Gemara right, but not ויכולו Vayechulu
of קידוש. Kiddush And the only reason you say ויכולו Vayechulu when
you get home is not for קידוש. Kiddush. It's because your rest
of your family hasn't דאוונד davened מעריב Maariv yet and they didn't
say the ויכולו Vayechulu that you're supposed to say during מעריב. Maariv.
One minute. ומה שרגילים לומר ויכולו אחר התפילה בקול רם. U'mah sheragilim
lomar Vayechulu achar hatefilla b'kol ram. If it's never part of this
like public ritual, if it's always just part of שמונה עשרה, Shmoneh
Esrei, why did we, well, you say it at home because people
aren't going to דאוון שמונה עשרה daven Shmoneh Esrei but it's so
important they say ויכולו. Vayechulu. Why do you say it in שול
shul after שמונה עשרה? Shmoneh Esrei? משום יום טוב שחל להיות בשבת
שמתפללים בו אתה בחרתנו ואין אומרים ויכולו בתפילה. Mishum Yom Tov shechal
lihayos b'Shabbos shemispallelim bo Atah Vechartanu v'ein omrim Vayechulu bitfilla. Because when
you have יום טוב Yom Tov on שבת, Shabbos. you don't say
ויכולו Vayechulu in שמונה עשרה Shmoneh Esrei of מעריב. Maariv. So therefore
that would be one scenario, maybe once a year, maybe, that you
won't say ויכולו Vayechulu in שמונה עשרה, Shmoneh Esrei, and every, they
want you to say ויכולו Vayechulu on Friday night in דאוונינג, davening,
not as קידוש. Kiddush And therefore the תקנה takana was to always
say ויכולו Vayechulu after שמונה עשרה. Shmoneh Esrei. Yeah. ותיקנו נמי לומר
בכל שבתות שלא לחלק בין שבת לשבת. V'tiknu nami lomar b'chol Shabbasos
shelo l'chaleik bein Shabbos l'Shabbos. So first of all, fascinating תוספות Tosafos,
about the nature of ויכולו. Vayechulu. ויכולו Vayechulu is not at all
part of קידוש. Kiddush, It's basically totally about תפילת מעריב Tefillas Maariv
of שבת. Shabbos They have, it then gets this independent identity afterwards
because of the one time in the year maybe that you won't
say it during מעריב. Maariv. Right? It gets, then we say it
at home because of people that aren't going to say it. So
it's actually interesting though, it's not just when you're דאוונינג מעריב davening
Maariv say this. There's obviously a point of saying ויכולו Vayechulu Friday
night, so you know, so therefore fundamentally in the שמונה עשרה Shmoneh
Esrei of מעריב, Maariv, but if that's not going to happen because
people aren't in שול shul or because it's יום טוב Yom Tov
or whatever, then you say it separately. But that's like independent of
the idea of saying קידוש. Kiddush, Of course for us it gets
wrapped all together. So that's number one, interesting understanding of ויכולו. Vayechulu.
Now עדות eidus and then it's where is, תוספות, Tosafos
I mean we conceive of it as עדות, eidus, we say two
people, two men are supposed to say it and etc. standing up.
תוספות Tosafos, isn't saying that, but there's an idea you say ויכולו,
Vayechulu, right, you commemorate שבת Shabbos that way. Now of course you
could say isn't that exactly זכרהו על היין evoking מעשה בראשית ma'aseh
bereishis and so on? But his point is to point out, at
least according to תוספות, Tosafos and the רמב"ם Rambam is very similar,
is that no, is that קידוש Kiddush is through the ברכות brachos
that חז"ל Chazal established. The saying of the פסוקים, psukim, you know,
it's sort of like we have a מצווה mitzvah of, standard analogy,
we're in פסחים, Pesachim, of telling over the סיפור יציאת מצרים, sippur
Yetzias Mitzrayim, but we don't do it by reading the פסוקים psukim
in שמות. Shmos. So we have a מצווה mitzvah of זכרהו על
היין, we don't say the זכירה zechira is by reading the פסוקים
psukim of ויכולו. Vayechulu. זכירה Zechira is the ברכות brachos that חז"ל
Chazal were מתקן. mesakein. Yes, they also said you should say ויכולו
Vayechulu when שבת Shabbat begins, but not as part of קידוש. Kiddush
That's the way תוספות Tosafos. understands it. רמב"ם Rambam is actually quite
similar. Now in terms of the issue, I'll read רמב"ם Rambam in
a second, but in terms of the issue about יין yayin and
קידוש Kiddush. and הבדלה, Havdalah, let's take a look. He says, back
in the גמרא? Gemara. No,
still back in תוספות. Tosafos Okay, but I want to see this
because obviously it's very central to understanding these ideas. He says, ונראה
דקידוש
על היין אסמכתא היא. V'nireh d'kiddush al hayayin asmachta hi. He says,
but you know what, at the end of the day, although I
said זכרו כיין Zichro k'yayin etc., those were פסוקים psukim in the
תורה, Torah, and it really seems like the whole idea of using
wine is only אסמכתא. asmachta. Okay. And then he brings in all
the discussion about that and then he says at the very end,
he says, but maybe not. He says, ועוד מצינו למימר, V'od matzinu
l'meimar, three lines before the תוספות Tosafot ends, the word starting with
the word מצינו, matzinu, דקידוש על היין. d'kiddush al hayayin. קידוש היום
דבר תורה. kiddush hayom dvar Torah. So how about certain גמרות Gemaras
that implies that biblically you don't have to drink the wine? He
says,
אלא הא דאמר מברך צריך שיטעום ela ha d'amar mevarech tzarich sheyit'om
זה מדרבנן. ze mid'rabbanan. It might only be rabbinic to drink the
wine, but it might be biblical to make it on the wine.
Very shocking idea that דאורייתא, d'Oraita, זכור יום השבת Zachor Yom HaShabbat
means you need to do it with the ritual of wine. You
know, we assume that you know that certainly you're יוצא yotzei your
דאורייתא d'Oraita by what you say in שול. shul. You know, again,
this issue by the way of ויכולו. Vayechulu. The assumption is, although
תוספות Tosafot says this isn't קידוש, Kiddush our assumption is you're יוצא
yotzei your דאורייתא d'Oraita obligation by saying ויכולו Vayechulu in שול, shul,
right? Whereas תוספות Tosafot says, oh ויכולו Vayechulu is something else, this
is קידוש, Kiddush. and all of a sudden like the קידוש דאורייתא
Kiddush d'Oraita might be exactly and only sort of what חז"ל Chazal
were מתקן, metakkein, you know, the ברכה bracha plus the wine. Okay?
But so that is interesting. I'll just read you for a second
the רמב"ם. Rambam. I'll just read you for a second the רמב"ם
Rambam on this. The רמב"ם Rambam says
hold on
if you left a סדר seder
yeah this is so amazing, this little thing here. Hold on can
I ask while you
find it?
No, just wait one second. Okay.
So the רמב"ם Rambam is, מצות עשה מן התורה, mitzvah asei min
haTorah, this is פרק כ"ט, perek kaf-tet, מצות עשה מן התורה לקדש
את יום השבת בדברים, mitzvah asei min haTorah l'kaddesh et yom HaShabbat
bidvarim, with words. שנאמר זכור את יום השבת לקדשו. shene'emar Zachor et
yom HaShabbat l'kaddesho. כלומר
זכרהו זכירת שבח וקידוש, klomar zachrehu zechirat shevach v'kiddush,
קידוש Kiddush, not meaning in the technical sense, sanctifying it. Praising and
sanctifying it. וצריך לזכרהו בכניסתו וביציאתו. v'tzarich l'zachrehu b'knisato u'v'yetziato. בכניסתו בקידוש
היום וביציאתו בהבדלה. b'knisato b'Kiddush Hayom u'v'yetziato b'Havdalah.
So it makes it sound very clear that according to the רמב"ם,
Rambam, הבדלה Havdalah is דאורייתא d'Oraita as well. וזהו נוסח קידוש היום
בשבת v'zehu nusach Kiddush Hayom b'Shabbat blah blah blah. וזהו נוסח הבדלה
ברוך אתה ה' v'zehu nusach Havdalah Baruch Atah Hashem etc. So he
basically totally equates קידוש Kiddush, and הבדלה Havdalah as playing an equal
function. עיקר קידוש בלילה, ikar Kiddush balailah,
okay, what we do at the day is not real קידוש. Kiddush
I'm just reading the chapter headings of each section here, or whatever,
the section headings.
אסור לאדם לאכול ולשתות משקידש היום עד שיקדש assur l'adam le'echol u'lishtot
mishekiddesh hayom ad sheyikaddesh and then similar by הבדלה Havdalah you can't
eat after it gets dark. ו'. Vav. מדברי סופרים לקדש על היין
ולהבדיל על היין. midivrei sofrim l'kaddesh al hayayin u'l'havdil al hayayin. Okay,
so on the one hand emphasizing that הבדלה Havdalah is דאורייתא, d'Oraita,
תוספות Tosafot didn't address it. Number two, though, and the קידוש Kiddush
in the day is not the real קידוש. Kiddush And number three,
though, that the יין yayin is clearly דרבנן, d'rabbanan, which is clearly
the, you know, the large consensus. And then I'll just read you
one other thing about the, about the ויכולו. Vayechulu.
He says
hold on, I think he has the ויכולו Vayechulu one minute hold
on if I
can't I'll just see if I can find it quickly yeah.
מנהג
ומברך על הגפן ואחר כך מקדש minhag u'mevarech al hagefen v'achar kach
mekaddesh when he discusses how you do it. ומנהג פשוט בכל ישראל
לקרוא בתחילה פרשת ויכולו ואחר כך מברך על היין ואחר כך מקדשין
ושותה מלא לוגמיו. u'minhag pashut b'chol Yisrael likrot b'tchilah parshat Vayechulu v'achar
kach mevarech al hayayin v'achar kach mekaddeshin v'shoteh m'lo lugmav. So a
little clearly like תוספות Tosafot makes it clear that that's not part
of the תקנה takkanah of חז"ל Chazal saying ויכולו, Vayechulu, okay, but
still a little more than תוספות Tosafot makes it sound like the
מנהג minhag is, which is clearly our מנהג, minhag, not סתם stahm
oh I'll say ויכולו Vayechulu and then ten minutes later I'll make
קידוש, Kiddush you know, it's the מנהג minhag is to incorporate ויכולו
Vayechulu into the קידוש, Kiddush which is clearly what we do. And
look and that's why we also assume that the ויכולו Vayechulu serves
that function and דאורייתא d'Oraita you fulfill your obligation if you say
ויכולו Vayechulu as well. So not as independent from the קידוש Kiddush.
as תוספות Tosafot would have it.
Yes, that's what I was going to ask about ויכולו. Vayechulu. So
that just means according to תוספות Tosafot and I already went to
שול shul and
I come home, I don't need to do ויכולו Vayechulu right in
the home? Right, right. Again, you could still say still that the,
you know, that it was the מנהג minhag to do it that
way for the cases when... I don't know what תוספות Tosafot would
say in that case. Yes. What? Go ahead, yeah?
Is it... I don't know if you want to comment on הלכות
halakhot of קידוש Kiddush of the day, but, you know, I'd be
interested in hearing your opinions, but we still have to do as
I'm trying to get this straight, we still have to do קידוש
Kiddush? during the day because of קידוש במקום סעודה, Kiddush b'makom seudah,
right?
Exactly, that's my point. My point is at the end of the
day, it doesn't... it's just בורא פרי הגפן, Borei Pri HaGafen but
it's not like the רמב"ם Rambam would have as wine during שלוש
סעודות shalosh seudot by the fact that it does get some קידוש
Kiddush. status, it has to be במקום סעודה b'makom seudah although the
מקום סעודה makom seudah according to the רמב"ם Rambam is by שלוש
סעודות shalosh seudot too, but it has to also precede the eating
and you're not allowed to eat before you make קידוש Kiddush, in
the day. Yes, Charlie.
Very often when I make it to שול shul Paula doesn't and
she'll make קידוש.
Kiddush Okay,
good to know. Thank you.
והקשיא לקשיא, v'hakashia l'kashia, right?
Okay, let's move on. So, alright. So, אמרי בני רבי חייא, amrei
bnei Rabbi Chiya, so the children of רבי חייא Rabbi Chiya said,
מי שלא הבדיל במוצאי שבת מבדיל והולך כל השבת כולה. mi shelo
hivdil b'motzei Shabbat mavdil v'holech kol HaShabbat kulo. So I think we
said this before, somebody who did not make הבדלה מוצאי שבת, Havdalah
motzei Shabbat, that we said if you didn't make קידוש Kiddush. Friday
night you can make it through שבת Shabbat day. If you didn't
make הבדלה מוצאי שבת, Havdalah motzei Shabbat, you could make it later
in the week. עד כמה? ad kamah? How late in the week?
אמר רבי זירא amar Rabbi Zeira עד רביעי בשבת, ad revii b'Shabbat,
until Tuesday. Until... I mean... until Wednesday. Until Wednesday, through Tuesday.
Through Tuesday night or? Through, no, through the end of Tuesday day.
Once it's Tuesday night, it's halachically Wednesday, you can't. Okay, but Sunday,
Monday, Tuesday are connected to the previous שבת Shabbat and Wednesday, Thursday,
Friday are connected to the coming שבת Shabbat so you can still
demarcate שבת Shabbat. through those days. Pretty funny you've been doing מלאכה,
melacha, presumably you've been eating those three days, somehow it still serves
as an act of demarcation.
Shai used that פסוק from קהלת, Kohelet, did he explain that?
Yeah, he was just saying, I had good foresight, I was...
He looked around
and, he not only looked around, I had good foresight to think
that I have to make a בורא פרי הגפן Borei Pri HaGafen...
anyway and to sort of figure out how I'm going to
do that, so...
בורא פרי הגפן... Borei Pri HaGafen Alright. Now,
כי הא, ki ha, now, כי הא דייתיב ki ha deyasiv רבי
זירא Rabbi Zeira קמיה דרב אסי, kamma deRav Assi, or maybe it
was רב אסי Rav Assi sitting in front of
רבי יוחנן, Rabbi Yochanan, ויתיב וקאמר. yativ vekamar.
For גיטין Gittin purposes, גט Get is often used as an example
of things that people would stipulate on, that things haven't changed at
all. But in the time of the גמרא Gemara it was not
that type of extortion stipulation. The גמרא Gemara. sort of used it
more as a way of sort of just dealing with this whole
idea of like making things that take effect conditionally. So like, this
will be your גט Get on the condition that you do X,
Y, and Z after שבת. Shabbat. Or on the condition that you
know, it could be you give me a hundred dollars, you know,
or on the condition that you do so and so before שבת.
Shabbat? So the question is what's defined as after שבת? Shabbat, Every
day is after שבת, Shabbat. it's always after another previous שבת. Shabbat,
So it says if you make a stipulation after שבת, Shabbat. then
Sunday, anytime Sunday, Monday, or Tuesday count as after שבת. Shabbat, If
you make a stipulation about that it has to be done before
שבת, Shabbat so ארבעה דחמשה ומעלי יומא קמי שבתא. arba dechamisha umala
yoma kamma shabbata. So Wednesday, Thursday, and Friday is counted as the
before שבת Shabbat period. So halachically those days have the identity of
after שבת Shabbat or before שבת Shabbat, and that has relevance for
the הבדלה. Havdalah. אמר רבי יעקב בר אידי, Amar Rabbi Yaakov bar
Idi, said רבי יעקב בר אידי, Rabbi Yaakov bar Idi, אבל
לא על האור. aval lo al ha’ur. This idea that you can
make it up through Tuesday is not by the fire. Why is
that? Because the fire, as I mentioned to you, is the idea
that
the
תחילת יצירה של האור techilas yitzirah shel ha’ur was מוצאי שבת. Motzei
Shabbat. So that, you know, you want specifically at that exactly at
the מוצאי שבת Motzei Shabbat period. Of course you could say the
whole idea of הבדלה Havdalah is to draw the line and it's
too late to draw the line. But presumably הבדלה Havdalah just recognizes
more that there's been a transition. So as long as you're still
somehow within the shadow, you know, within the ambit of it, you
can acknowledge that a transition occurred. But to commemorate this particular event
of the אש, esh, that you want to do only at when
that occurred on מוצאי שבת Motzei Shabbat itself. אמר רב ברונא אמר
רב. Amar Rav Bruna Amar Rav. Said רב ברונא Rav Bruna in
the name of רב. Rav. You thought we weren't going to finish,
I knew what was coming at look at. הנוטל ידיו, Hanotel yadav,
now you got the Yekkis are going to like this discussion. So,
can you do wash your hands and then make קידוש? Kiddush Do
נטילת ידיים. Netilat Yadayim.
הנוטל ידיו לא יקדש. Hanotel yadav lo yekadesh. Once you wash your
hands you cannot make קידוש. Kiddush. Why? Because, at least the way
the רשב"ם Rashbam explains it, it would be a הפסק. hefsek. You
did נטילת ידיים, Netilat Yadayim, you have to do המוציא. Hamotzi. You
can’t do בורא פרי הגפן Borei Pri HaGafen in the middle. So
what the רשב"ם Rashbam says is you can still be quiet and
hear somebody else’s קידוש, Kiddush but for you to actually make קידוש
Kiddush now would be a הפסק hefsek and therefore you cannot make
קידוש. Kiddush And if there’s nobody else around then maybe you’d have
no choice and you’d have to go ahead and make קידוש Kiddush
and do another נטילת ידיים. Netilat Yadayim. But ideally, you should not
be interrupting your נטילת ידיים Netilat Yadayim with your קידוש. kiddush אמר
להו Amar lehu so אמר לרב יצחק בר שמואל בר מרתא. Amar
leRav Yitzchak bar Shmuel bar Marta. So רב יצחק בר שמואל בר
מרתא Rav Yitzchak bar Shmuel bar Marta said to him, עדיין לא
נח נפשיה דרב. adayin lo nach nafshih deRav. רב Rav isn't even
cold in the ground
yet, ושכחנינהו לשמעתתיה. veshachachnihu lishmeiteih. And we've already forgotten his teachings. Okay,
what is this idea you're saying? Like, I mean you're forgetting what
רב Rav used to teach? זימנין סגיאין הוי קאימנא קמיה דרב. Zimnin
sagi'in havei kamina kameih deRav. Many times I was in the presence
of רב. Rav.
I got to tell you by the way a little parenthetical thing,
I don't know if you've noticed, but how much
מעשה רב, Ma'aseh Rav, and I don't mean רב Rav the person,
how many like actual observed practices are being brought into the discussion,
so much more than in other areas, you know, because קידוש Kiddush
and הבדלה Havdalah happens all the time, every single שבת, Shabbos you
know, you're doing this ritual and you're seeing interesting things. So there's
just so many discussions here about actual things that people observed and
saw which we don't get most of the other time.
There's no
state into which everyone needs to do it the exact same way.
Why did he do it that way?
Right, well also the הלכה halachah, was a lot more in flux
at this time too.
זימנין סגיאין הוי קאימנא קמיה דרב. Zimnin sagi'in havei kamina kameih deRav.
There were many times I was in the presence of רב. Rav.
זימנין דחביבא ליה ריפתא מקדש אריפתא. Zimnin dechaviva leih rifta mekadesh arifta.
Sometimes he was interested in bread, he made קידוש kiddush on bread.
זימנין דחביבא ליה חמרא מקדש אחמרא. Zimnin dechaviva leih chamra mekadesh achamra.
Times he was interested in wine, he made קידוש kiddush on wine.
Now, what does this have to do with whether saying קידוש kiddush
is a הפסק? hefsek? Right? Meaning first of all let's point out,
what he did is he introduced this idea we yes he has
heard of at all, which is that you can make קידוש kiddush
on bread, right? Bizarre idea, whoever heard of that? קידוש kiddush is
on wine, of course קידוש kiddush is on wine. Now, and but
nevertheless, because he just throws it out there, it's assumed by the
רשב"ם, Rashbam, by the רמב"ם, Rambam, by almost all פוסקי poske פוסקים,
poskim, שולחן ערוך Shulchan Aruch takes it for granted, like doesn't even
bother make a big point about it or whatever, anyway, I'm overstating
it a little bit, but anyway, but you can make קידוש kiddush
on bread if you don't have wine or you're not interested in
wine and so on, which of course makes everything he said like
all these earlier discussions, you didn't have wine, what do you do,
how many כוסות cosos it's like, what, now you're just סתם stam
dropping this bomb that you can make קידוש kiddush on bread? So
nevertheless, that's how many פוסקים poskim assume because it's just sort of
assumed here. But it is worth pointing out that רבינו תם Rabbeinu
Tam says that that's not פשט pshat at all, you cannot make
קידוש kiddush on bread, no no, you totally misunderstood the גמרא. Gemara
And when it says because because number one, it's just completely radical,
number two was, there's a logical problem here. How is it relevant
to say oh look, רב Rav used to make קידוש kiddush on
bread? Okay, but if you're making קידוש kiddush on wine, how do
you know you're allowed to interrupt your נטילת ידים netilat yadayim with
your קידוש kiddush between your נטילת ידים netilat yadayim and your eating
the bread? What relevance is it that he would sometimes make קידוש
kiddush. on bread? How is that relevant? So תוספות Tosafot says the
only way to explain this גמרא Gemara according to that idea that
it means literally you can make קידוש kiddush on bread is no,
רב Rav would sometimes wash his hands to make קידוש kiddush on
bread and then he would change his mind and he would wind
up making it on wine. So I mean the punchline is missed,
okay, but that's how he reads this גמרא. Gemara, Ah, how do
you say it's an interruption? רב Rav would sometimes make קידוש kiddush
on bread, parenthetically, and wind up doing it on wine at the
end, and he would interrupt his נטילת ידים. netilat yadayim. So that's
one way of reading this. But the way תוספות Tosafot reads it
is you can't make קידוש kiddush on bread. He says here's what
it means, he says we have by the way forgotten something. We
have forgotten way back at the beginning of the פרק perek a
very interesting position that רב Rav has about קידוש. kiddush Does anybody
remember the very first discussion we had about קידוש kiddush at the
beginning of the פרק perek between רב Rav and שמואל Shmuel was
about making קידוש kiddush in the שול? shul? And רב Rav said,
anybody remember, that you can make קידוש שלא במקום סעודה? kiddush shelo
b'makom seudah? So he says what the גמרא Gemara means when רב
Rav was wanted to make קידוש kiddush on bread, he didn't mean
he said המוציא לחם Hamotzi Lechem and then he said מקדש השבת,
Mekadesh Hashabbat, it means when he was interested in having his קידוש
kiddush together with bread, when he was interested in having a meal,
he would actually make sure to have a meal and when not,
he would just do it on wine. Basically רב's Rav's position of
אין קידוש ein kiddush or that you can have קידוש kiddush, without
מקום סעודה. makom seudah. So how's that relevant to this question of
interruption? Because תוספות Tosafot, says the issue of washing before קידוש kiddush
is not an issue of making a הפסק. hefsek. There's no problem
of הפסק, hefsek, you're going straight from קידוש kiddush, into the meal,
the קידוש kiddush is connected to the meal, there's no הפסק hefsek
problem. Why should it be a problem of doing the קידוש kiddush
between נטילת ידים? netilat yadayim? By the way, they did
נטילת ידים netilat yadayim before המוציא, Hamotzi, that's also...
Well okay, but the only problem is that according to רב Rav
of אין קידוש אלא במקום סעודה, ein kiddush ela b'makom seudah, here's
the problem. I'll wash my hands, I'll make קידוש, kiddush and then
I'll decide, you know what, forget about the meal, I'm not hungry
about the meal. I have nothing compelling me to make the המוציא,
Hamotzi, right, because I don't need קידוש במקום סעודה. kiddush b'makom seudah.
So that was the question. The question was, can you wash and
make קידוש Kiddush, and are we concerned that you'll forget that you'll
just drop the meal? And then your נטילת ידים netilat yadayim will
have been a ברכה לבטלה. beracha l'vatala. Completely reframing what the concern
was, okay? And the answer was, I don't understand, רב Rav would
always do that, you know, he'd wash, he'd make קידוש, Kiddush he'd
plan to make המוציא, Hamotzi, he wouldn't be concerned, sometimes he wouldn't
make המוציא, Hamotzi, but when he would be making המוציא, Hamotzi, he
would do it with that assumption and he'd wash and he wouldn't
be concerned that he'd change his mind in the middle. So completely
re-reads, completely re-reads this גמרא Gemara. and says you cannot make קידוש
Kiddush on bread on the one hand, but number two, introduces nicely,
ties into this idea of רב Rav saying you don't need מקום
סעודה, makom seudah, so the issue of bread was, was he doing
it במקום סעודה b'makom seudah or not, not was he making קידוש
Kiddush on bread. But number three, what it also winds up saying
is that there's absolutely no problem of a הפסק hefsek because and
that was not the concern at all. The concern was just you
would forget about making the bread. But there was no issue of
a הפסק. hefsek. And then it becomes the question about what is
the הלכה למעשה. halacha l'maaseh.
Because according to the way the רשב"ם Rashbam reads it is like,
oh, we're concerned about a הפסק. hefsek. What do you mean? רב
Rav would do it and sometimes change his mind and he's not
concerned. So it still leaves a little bit of an issue of
maybe there's a הפסק hefsek concern. According to תוספות, Tosafot by his
re-read of the גמרא, Gemara there was never even a question that
it was, of course it's not a הפסק. hefsek. The only issue
is like would he, would he have like you know forgotten about
doing the bread at the end. So תוספות Tosafot says, so if
you take a look in תוספות Tosafot in terms of the הלכה,
halachah he says the following,
he says, he says like this, he says, ומאן
דסבר,
u-man
d'savar, it's three wide lines in the תוספות Tosafot at the beginning
of the line, ומאן דסבר אין קידוש אלא במקום סעודה, u-man d'savar
ein kiddush ela b'makom seudah, but if you're not like רב Rav
where we're not afraid that you that you can be יוצא yotzei
קידוש Kiddush without סעודה, seudah, you have to have סעודה, seudah, כל
שכן kol sheken דנוטל ידיו ומקדש. d'notel yadav u-mekadesh. So it wouldn't
be a הפסק *hefsek*, there's no question it wouldn't be a הפסק
*hefsek* if you have to do it במקום סעודה Bimkom Seudah. *bimkom
se'udah*, and number one, and number two, you're certainly not going to
drop doing it. And therefore he says,
anyway, and then I'm trying to find the line, but anyway, and
that totally then is the מנהג *minhag* of the אשכנזים *Ashkenazim*, I
think it's somewhere in this תוספות *Tosafos*, I just lost the place
right here, that the מנהג *minhag* of the אשכנזים *Ashkenazim* that they
totally wash and make קידוש Kiddush? *Kiddush* and make המוציא *Hamotzi*. So
the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* that made it sound that it was like
problematic to do that, right, to wash and make קידוש Kiddush *Kiddush*
and make המוציא *Hamotzi*, and maybe you had to argue it for
תוספות *Tosafos*, that was only because it was working within רב *Rav*,
and for רב *Rav* you didn't need מקום סעודה makom se'udah. *makom
se'udah*. But for us that we need מקום סעודה *makom se'udah*, of
course it's not a problem. And the אשכנזי *Ashkenazi* in the sense
of the German, the ייקי *Yekke* מנהג *minhag* is you wash, you
make קידוש Kiddush *Kiddush*, you make המוציא *Hamotzi*, which for us seems
so bizarre, because when I'm in a house that they do this,
like, what, isn't that a הפסק *hefsek*? But again, underscores the connection
of קידוש Kiddush. במקום סעודה Bimkom Seudah. *Kiddush bimkom se'udah*. It's all
wrapped together and it's very tightly connected. And for תוספות *Tosafos*, again,
the whole issue was according to רב *Rav* who didn't need it
to be מקום סעודה *makom se'udah*. Okay, so where am I? Let's
just get back to the גמרא *Gemara*, just ground us back in
the גמרא *Gemara*. Okay, so he says, let's read again: זימנין דחביבא
עליה ריפתא מקדש אריפתא זימנין דחביבא עליה חמרא מקדש אחמרא *Zimnin d'chaviva
alei rifta mekadesh a-rifta, zimnin d'chaviva alei chamra mekadesh a-chamra*. So sometimes
he would do bread, sometimes wine. Again, per רשב"ם *Rashbam*, it means
he would do bread and then he changed his mind and do
wine, so certainly at least בדיעבד b'di'eved *b'diavad* it's okay if you've
washed to do wine afterwards. And according to תוספות *Tosafos*, נטילת
ידים *netilas yadayim*, yeah,
and it's not a הפסק *hefsek*, you don't have to do it
again.
Did he eat bread?
He did, but he would change his mind and not go straight
to the bread. He'd have wine between it. He would wash for
bread and then choose to make wine and then go on to
bread. So you see it's not a problem of doing a הפסק
*hefsek*. That's the way the רשב"ם *Rashbam* reads it, and תוספות *Tosafos*
reads it you see he was, you know, whatever, you see he
went ahead and he wasn't concerned that he would, that he would
not have bread afterwards, but he would always wash and then do
wine and then do bread. So you see that that is allowed
according to תוספות לכתחילה *Tosafos lechatchila*, according to the רשב"ם *Rashbam* at
least בדיעבד bedi-avad *b'diavad*. Okay, so yeah, there was now, there was
a question?
Yeah, so if you can't make קידוש Kiddush *Kiddush* on the bread,
and according to that opinion, why are you covering the bread, דקשיא
אל היין *d'kashia al hayayin*? It's like, it's not like I have
to go out of the room, according to the גמרא *Gemara* it
goes, oh, he's calling the כהן *Kohen* out of a ישראל *Yisrael*.
No, again, the basic reason of covering the bread is not is
because number one, I mean, if you do this idea of embarrassed
or whatnot, it's because the ברכה *bracha* that should come first when
you have bread out is המוציא *Hamotzi*. You have to have קידוש
Kiddush, *Kiddush* first,
so why is it outside of... No, because of מקדם ברכתנא מן
*mi-kadam birchatinan minyn*,
forget embarrassed.
Anyway, the real reason is what the גמרא *Gemara* says is that
it's that you have to introduce the meal with קידוש Kiddush *Kiddush*.
So if you don't want the bread out there before you've introduced
it, if the whole קידוש Kiddush. *Kiddush* is on the bread, then
that is what's introducing it. But if you're introducing it with the
wine, then you say it and then you bring out the bread.
It's what we learned at the beginning of the מסכת *masechet*. Now,
what, now I want to say something here, let me first see
if I can get this line in the ראש *Rosh* about the
order. One minute.
One minute.
Yeah, no, okay. But anyway, but okay, so that's one issue, which
is according to the גמרא *Gemara*, at least it's acceptable if you
wash to go ahead and to make קידוש Kiddush, *Kiddush*. That's the
way the רשב"ם *Rashbam* understands it, that he would wash for bread
and then change his mind and make קידוש Kiddush, *Kiddush*. And according
to the תוספות *Tosafos* understands it, again, just to repeat what I
said, it was only an issue for רב *Rav* who said that
you could separate the קידוש Kiddush *Kiddush* and the meal. But for
us that קידוש Kiddush במקום סעודה Bimkom Seudah *Kiddush bimkom se'udah*, there's
absolutely no question, and therefore he would actually say, and this is
the German מנהג *minhag*, to wash, make קידוש *Kiddush*, דוקא *davka* to
wash, make קידוש *Kiddush* and then make המוציא *Hamotzi*. Now, Joe asked
before the question about not wine, but about
other types of beverages. So if you look at תוספות *Tosafos*, תוספות
*Tosafos* says like this,
he says like this,
וצריך עיון *v'tzarich iyun*, the line starts with the word מקדשין *mekadshin*,
it's about six lines down in the wide lines, it says וצריך
עיון אם מקדשין על השכר היכא דהוי חמר מדינה כמו שמבדילין *v'tzarich
iyun im mekadshin al hashechar heicha d'havei chamar medina k'mo she-mavdilin*. So
חמר מדינה *chamar medina*, which you'll see is like a type of
a social drink like beer and something like that, not a drink
just for thirst. The basic definition of חמר מדינה *chamar medina* is
something you drink in order to socialize even if you're not thirsty.
Okay, that's a good way of thinking of what חמר מדינה *chamar
medina* is. Okay, so the גמרא *Gemara* says you could use that
for הבדלה Havdalah. *Havdalah*. Can you use it for קידוש *Kiddush*? There's
all this emphasis of wine, but according to some, we've now been
introduced to the idea that you can even use bread. So if
you can use wine, you can use bread, maybe you could use
חמר מדינה *chamar medina*, who knows? Although you could say no, wine
and bread are still very distinct. So he goes through a whole
discussion. If you look at the very last line of that תוספות
*Tosafos*, after there's a period and then it
says מסקנא דמילתא *maskana de-miltha*, the conclusion is מבדילו
*mavdilu*. Why do you think that would be? Even those
that say you use bread for קידוש, you can't use it for
הבדלה. Havdalah. Why do you think that would be? Even those that
say you use bread for קידוש, you can't use it for הבדלה.
Havdalah Why?
You're not allowed to have a meal, so what?
Because קידוש has to be במקום סעודה. Bimkom Seudah הבדלה Havdalah. doesn't
have to be במקום סעודה. Bimkom Seudah. So קידוש is very much
about defining the meal, so you can use the bread itself for
the קידוש because it's about, it's connection and defining the meal. You
can't use the bread for the הבדלה. Havdalah, So on the one
hand, you have an option by הבדלה, Havdalah, you don't by קידוש
you don't have by הבדלה, Havdalah. which is making it on bread.
How about the חמרא מדינה? Chamra Medinah? That you can use for
הבדלה. Havdalah Can you use it for קידוש? So he says, ורבינו
תם
אין מקדשין על הפת, V'Rabbeinu Tam Ein Mekadshin Al Hapas, like as
I told you. אך יש לי ספק אם מקדשין על השכר. Ach
Yesh Li Safek Im Mekadshin Al Hashechar. So on the one hand,
bread yes for קידוש because it's about the meal. On the other
hand, maybe, maybe חמרא מדינה Chamra Medinah is only for הבדלה Havdalah
because maybe for הבדלה Havdalah? it's more, it's less about, because it's
less about the meal, you have more options in terms of what
types of liquids, any liquid that gives it some weight. Whereas if
it's about the meal, wine and bread connect something much more to
the
meal than does like חמרא מדינה. Chamra Medinah. So his, that's his
question. The basic practice is to be much more מקפיד makpid on
wine on Friday night and to generally assume that שבת Shabbos day
when you, you know, that there's a lot more latitude and that
you can use חמרא מדינה. Chamra Medinah. I'm pretty מקפיד makpid personally
as I think I've mentioned before, not to use grape juice because
you know, it's very questionable if grape juice really constitutes יין, yayin,
but I'm much more מקפיד makpid about that on Friday night. שבת
day when you can anyways, it's generally פסק paskened use חמרא מדינה
Chamra Medinah to assume that, you know,
you can use grape juice as well. I will say another thing
about the issue, again, we haven't really discussed חמרא מדינה, Chamra Medinah,
but it's one thing to discuss whether or not you can use
other liquids. It's another thing what the שיעור shiur is. The שיעור
shiur is still supposed to be a רביעית, revi'is, three and a
half ounces. So if you've got some nice single malt Scotch you
want to make קידוש on it, you need three and a half
ounces of it,
maybe don't drink the רוב רביעית, rov revi'is, but who knows, but
anyway, you won't make it home. And the whole argument that you
can use a more
proportionate שיעור shiur for what is norm for that liquid is very
late. Even in the discussions of חמרא מדינה Chamra Medinah in the
גמרא and the ראשונים Rishonim or whatever, the complete assumption is you're
going to do a רביעית. revi'is. So I sometimes tell people if
they want to do this, is whatever the scenario is, like I
think it's like sometimes on a, you know, they don't have wine
around or it's... ah, sometimes it's like a question during the nine
days what to make it on and so on. So I'll say,
so just make a mixed drink. Like you know, do like orange
juice and vodka, right? So it's easy to get three and a
half ounces if you have a mixed drink. You don't have to
drink it all out of straight liquor. That's also חמרא מדינה. Chamra
Medinah. Alright, let's do a little bit more in the גמרא. Yes?
Why is there a question about בורא פרי הגפן Borei Pri HaGafen
on grape juice? Because it's not alcohol?
No, בורא פרי הגפן on grape... well because it's not יין, yayin,
because you don't... you know, the גמרא's special status that it gives
to יין yayin might only apply to... but it doesn't have alcohol.
No, the גמרא does say that unfermented wine, even one-day-old unfermented wine
is still wine, but that's wine that can ferment. Our grape juice
is pasteurized and can no longer become wine and it might be
completely out of the category of יין. yayin.
It's like מבושל. mevushal.
Yeah. Alright, let's read a little bit more. Okay. So בעי מיניה
רב
חנא בר חיננא מאמר רב הונא: Ba'ei Minei Rav Chana Bar Chinana
M'amar Rav Huna: טעם מהו שיבדיל? Ta'am Mahu Sheyavdil? The issue raised
before: if you taste, can you still make הבדלה? Havdalah? Did I
miss a line? Okay, thanks. אמר רב הונא אמר רב: Amar Rav
Huna Amar Rav:
טעם אינו מקדש. Ta'am Eino Mekadesh. If you had something to eat,
you can't make קידוש. Fine. בעי מיניה רב חנא בר חיננא מאמר
רב הונא: Ba'ei Minei Rav Chana Bar Chinana M'amar Rav Huna: טעם
מהו שיבדיל? Ta'am Mahu Sheyavdil? How about הבדלה? Havdalah? Again, קידוש במקום
סעודה is much more about קידוש, so you could say if you've
already began your meal, it's not appropriate for you, like when do
we ever get a penalty, 'Ah, you did something wrong, now you
can't make'? But if the idea of במקום סעודה is it defines
the beginning of your eating, so if you've already begun eating, the
importance of making קידוש is much less, is much... the significance is
less. So if you've already eaten, you can't make קידוש. How about
הבדלה? Havdalah, That's not... yes, you're not supposed to eat before הבדלה,
Havdalah. but it's... there's not an idea of במקום סעודה. So its
connection to the eating is not as... is not as tight and
therefore maybe if בדיעבד bedi-avad you ate, you can make הבדלה. Havdalah.
טעם מהו שיבדיל? Ta'am Mahu Sheyavdil? אמר ליה אני
אומר טעם מבדיל. Amar Lei Ani Omer Ta'am Mavdil. I say if
you tasted something, you can still make הבדלה. Havdalah, ורב אסי אמר
טעם אינו מבדיל. V'Rav Assi Amar Ta'am Eino Mavdil. רב אסי Rav
Assi says you can't. רבי ירמיה... Rabbi Yirmiyah... now one story and
we'll end with this. רבי ירמיה בר אבא איקלע לבי רב אסי.
Rabbi Yirmiyah Bar Abba Ikla L'vei Rav Assi. רבי ירמיה בר אבא
Rabbi Yirmiyah Bar Abba came to the house of רב אסי Rav
Assi who said, who said that you can't make הבדלה, Havdalah, another
story. אישתלי, Ishtali, he forgot, רבי ירמיה, Rabbi Yirmiyah, וטעים מידי, v'ta'im
midei, and he had a little bit to eat after it got
dark. הבו ליה כסא, Havu Lei Kassa, so they gave him a
cup to make הבדלה, Havdalah, ואבדיל, v'avdil, and he went out and
he made הבדלה, Havdalah okay, even though he had already tasted something.
אמרה ליה דביתהו, Amrah Lei Deviseihu, so רב אסי's Rav Assi wife
said to him, the hostess said to רב אסי, Rav Assi, the
host, so you know, said to him... והא מר לא עביד הכי
Veha Mar lo avid hachi but the master you, אבי, Abi, you
don't do this, you won't make הבדלה Havdalah if you've tasted something.
Quite fascinating, right? It means that it's happened often enough that he
accidentally ate, that she knows that he won't make הבדלה Havdalah, if
he happened to eat. Anyway, if you happen to eat, you don't
make הבדלה, Havdalah? so what is he doing that he's making הבדלה?
Havdalah. He ate something. אמר ליה, Amar lei, so he said back,
שבקיה, shavkei, leave him alone, דרבינו, de-rabbinu, leave him alone, whoever רבי
ירמיה Rabbi Yirmiyah who made הבדלה. Havdalah דרביה סבירא ליה, De-rabbei seivira
lei, he holds like his rabbi, his rabbi is,
who was his rabbi? רב הונא, Rav Huna, he holds like רב
הונא. Rav Huna. So fine, I don't do it, he does do
it, so let him do what he does, it's okay. All right.
And I guess one more line because it's just repeating the different
opinions. אמר רב יוסף אמר שמואל, Amar Rav Yosef amar Shmuel, טעם
אינו מקדש טעם אינו מבדיל. tam eino mekadesh tam eino mavdil. Same
הלכה, you can't do it for קידוש, you can't do it for
הבדלה Havdalah, if you've eaten, you no longer qualify. ורבה אמר רב
נחמן אמר שמואל, Verabba amar Rav Nachman amar Shmuel, טעם מקדש וטעם
מבדיל, tam mekadesh ve-tam mavdil, בדיעבד you can do it for both.
ואמר רבא, Ve-amar Rava, הלכתא, hilchasa, the הלכה is, טעם
מקדש וטעם מבדיל. tam mekadesh ve-tam mavdil. בדיעבד you can do it
for both.
But again the possible differences are interesting because of the way in
which they both are connected to food. You can't eat before קידוש,
you can't eat before הבדלה, Havdalah. but קידוש is more connected to
the meal because of מקום סעודה. And that's also why תוספות says
you can use bread for קידוש and you can't use bread for
הבדלה. So interesting to see these differences.